Jack: A coding professional needs
to have strong IT skills and good
knowledge of systems including
hardware, software, and networks.
It is also helpful for them to have a
good understanding of the systems in
place within the business or area in which
they will be working, and they should be
fully conversant with coding languages
relevant to their programming area.
Leah: They should also know what coding
languages will work best in relation
to their function such as website
creation, software programming, database
development or programming operating
systems, security, or data architecture.
The four main job functions of
a programmer are to write, test,
debug and maintain the code that
creates the programmes that computers
follow to perform their functions.
They are responsible for the design
and development and to ensure that the
software adheres to best practices in
performance, reliability, and security.
They can work in developing mobile
apps, coding video games, programming
websites and can work freelance or in
a multitude of different industries.
Jack: Let's have a look at what other key
skills coding professionals should have.
Like many other complex professions
programming requires a particular
skill set to be successful.
However, being a coding professional
is not just about knowing all about
computers and coding language and
programming, there are other key
skills that are relevant to the role.
Let’s have a look at some of these.
Leah: Positive attitude
When writing code, a positive and
proactive attitude is sometimes needed
as you may often have to go the extra
mile to create a successful product.
A positive attitude is also important
if you need to provide instructions
or comments on a piece of code, which
should be clear and instructive.
If there are problems, it is important to
be constructive and solution orientated.
Jack: Communication
Coders are often required to write code
so that others including other coders will
be able to understand and maintain it.
They will also need to be able to
explain complex concepts, like how
something works, or the reasons
behind things to non-coders like
clients in relatively simple terms.
The ability to communicate effectively,
can make all the difference in
getting their ideas over to others.
Leah: Teamwork
Most developers are part of a team
and should be able to share their
ideas and support the ideas of others.
This may involve disagreements and
debate, but this can help develop
differing ideas to reach a common goal.
Members of the team may have different
functions, but it may involve them all
working at different stages of the process
to ultimately ensure a successful outcome.
Jack: Time Management
Time management is essential for a coding
professional not getting distracted from
the task at hand, knowing what is needed,
and being able to stick to deadlines and
produce high quality work consistently.
The ability to meet targets and get it
right the first time is the best approach,
extra features can be added later
when the programme is up and running.
Leah: Problem solving
A coder should be good at problem
solving because this is what they do,
understanding how to solve problems
within the software they are programming.
It doesn't matter how knowledgeable
they are, they may come across something
that is far from straightforward
and needs to be worked out.
Being able to break down a problem
into its component parts, then
finding a solution, is a vital skill.
Jack: Self-motivation
Learning to code can be difficult,
so a programmer must be able to
motivate themselves to stick to
it even when things go wrong.
They also need to have patience, so as not
to get stressed when de bugging code or
working with a difficult system or client.
Leah: Analytical skills
Code must be visualised to work
out what outcomes need to be
created and the processes involved.
Coders need to draw analytical
conclusions from things that may on
the surface seem straightforward.
Curiosity can also help a coder push
themselves to try new approaches.